[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have a few suttas that I would like to go through.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: This theme is really about sense restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha gave a short teaching to Bahiya.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gave a short teaching to Malonkeya Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: The same verse.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I'll just read out Nyanaviru's translation of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, bahir, you should train your... train thus.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the seen, there shall be just the seen.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the heard, there shall be just the heard.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sensed, there shall be just the sensed.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the cognized, there shall be just the cognized.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, bahir, should you train yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: When, bahir, for you, in the seen, there shall be just the seen, the heard, just the sensed, just the cognized, then you will not
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when he says,
[SPEAKER_01]: You will not be that by which... you will not be in that place, and you'll not be here or any longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I think, here, yonder, and between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is that, you know?
[SPEAKER_01]: Here is the sense basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will neither be your sense places.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you neither... Yeah, yourself will neither be taken to be your sense places, or sense objects, or both, or neither, whichever.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, sometimes you can, through denial of things, you can establish your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can deny
[SPEAKER_00]: There is here, there is yonder, and in between the two, would stand basically for both here and yonder, and neither here nor yonder, the mental attitude in regard to the experience as a whole of here and yonder.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the self can always kind of, even through denial of it, can re-establish itself as not that, but implying I am something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Although there isn't anything else to be found simply through that denial.
[SPEAKER_00]: negation of something, you give enough space for the notion of self to remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that sense, basically, when in seeing, there is just the seeing, no amount of
[SPEAKER_00]: Movement, so to speak, of the mind, in regard to the I and the sights, and by the experience of the seen, no matter the movement, whether it's in it, apart from it, both in it or apart from it, whether it's mine, whether it's for me, whether it's this, none of that will induce the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: When seen, there is just the seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, in other words, when the seeing is not appropriate, when the senses that are seeing are not appropriate,
[SPEAKER_00]: When both, the senses and that which is being seen, are not appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, in the seen, there's just the seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're neither appropriating it, and appropriation is basically, eh... established either through indulging it, or running away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indulging it, or denying it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, you basically relate to it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that relation is a form of appropriation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why he doesn't... he doesn't either indulge the sights, nor does he fear them or run away from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: The scene is just a scene.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no need to do anything in regard to it, for and of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you have a pleasing sight or a displeasing sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasing sight is just a pleasing sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: For somebody who is not developed in regard to pleasing sight, pleasing sight would be inducing lust in their mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: The lust is not in the pleasing sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what the Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's another of Nyanavira's translations in the back of the book, saying that the target perceives beautiful objects in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: He still sees, oh, this is beautiful, this is agreeable, this is nice, but his thoughts do not have desire and lust in regard to those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's when people can't see that, can't see that the nature of desire and lust pertains to the mind, it's not in the objects, then they deny the objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: They try to overcome desire and lust through sheer denial of objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the sutta, the simile of the bait, in Majjhima Nikaya, where Cho, one deer herd, eats Mara's bait, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: enjoys the senses carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, because of that, Māra does with them what he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, another group of deer sees that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sees that the hunter controls this deer, does what he wants, because they're eating their traps unwarily.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they think, okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in, in
[SPEAKER_00]: They deny the entire sense sphere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in that sutta says the deer then shuns the bait completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Forgetting that they do depend on it to some extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: They shine, they go up in the mountains, but then, sooner or later, the food, the water runs out in the mountains, and they have to come back to their bed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because they were never developed in regard to the bed in the first place, they'll end up eating it carelessly, like the first day ahead.
[SPEAKER_00]: And again, in the end, Mara does with them what he wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's exactly like the indulgence and denial results in the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Results in you not being... not understanding the nature of debate and being controlled because of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is that, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The deer, herd, would recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would recognize the nature of the indulgence, the nature of denial.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it would stay within the domain of bait, because it depends on a certain extent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, it depends on food.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it would not eat carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the key.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would eat carefully.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be careful of the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you wouldn't deny everything, you wouldn't throw away the baby with the bathwater, it would basically start distinguishing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a very... well, it's not necessarily subtle, if the mind starts getting used to it, but for most people, it's a very subtle distinction, because people either say yes or no completely.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, you have to start with restraint first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Restraint in regard to things that are not necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such as sexual integrals, things based on excessive lust, things based on anger and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, eating food is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can do it lustfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can do it because of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, you can do it mindfully.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people who don't know, who can't distinguish that the lust is on them, not on the food,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they start denying food.
[SPEAKER_00]: They try void food.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, he says, that was happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Asceticism.
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-mortification.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that will... sooner or later, that won't be enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, they start denying more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it can go as far as denying breathing, denying air, denying anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha tried that and he said, no, this is not the way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, that doesn't mean that, okay, so now you should go back and eat everything unwarily again.
[SPEAKER_00]: And be completely unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's... that's as silly as, you know, as it can be.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha was quite clear how one should then practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you develop the virtue first, you develop the strength, you stop doing unwholesome things that are completely unnecessary and they have... like inexcusable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, other things, like, you know, you won't have... you can't help by encountering agreeable sights, agreeable sounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're just blaming sights and sounds, well, the Buddha again said, you won't be different than a blind or a deaf man, if you think that the domain of sight, domain of sound, is the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's desire and lust in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of being the second deer that runs to the mountain in fear of the whole domain, no, you recognize that, so you stay within it, practice restraining to the extent necessary, but then, for the rest, you start developing mindfulness in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means eating the food carefully.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not being careless in regard to the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what the bait is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Carelessness.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what gives rise to lust, to aversion, to delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the actual food.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the actual sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how agreeable they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was that other quote you just read earlier on today?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll read it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, read it now, because it's exactly what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just before that, what you're saying now, because to shun the bait, seems to me, is a
[SPEAKER_01]: Is there some sort of ill will there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're pushing away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're averse towards that pleasing stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: Out of fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you fear that agreeable sight, sound, smell, taste, touch will induce lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you absolutely have no no recourse to prevent it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only way that you know how to get... push things away, the ill will... Well, you push away pleasing things and then
[SPEAKER_01]: You bring the things that displease you closer.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That hurts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then that becomes that which pleases you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You end up just acting in the same way like the first herd.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's... the other herd, they go... they see what the hunt is about, they see what the bait is about, and they've overcome him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He's kind of bewildered by...
[SPEAKER_00]: They stay there, but they don't eat the bait, so he can't see them, because they're never caught on the hooks.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the food is eaten around the bed.
[SPEAKER_01]: But is there really a bed?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or does the answer really exist?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just an illusion.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, it's not... That is the case.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the situation which you're born in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, that's all the gospel.
[SPEAKER_00]: People can deny it through all sorts of views and stuff, which is, of course, that's why the acknowledgment of those things has to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what we are talking about, we assume that we agree on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a different topic now.
[SPEAKER_00]: We agree that there is such thing as being controlled by the senses and being a victim to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is another sutta from Samyutta Nikaya and the chapter 35, verse 94.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's called Untamed or Unguarded.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, eh... the Buddha speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because these six bases for contact, if untamed, unguarded, unprotected, unrestrained, are bringers of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just six bhikkhus are the basis for contact, where one unrestrained meets with suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those who know how to restrain them dwell uncorrupted with faith they partner.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having seen forms that delight the mind, and having seen those that give no delight, dispel the path of lust towards the delightful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having seen the delightful, it doesn't say run away from delightful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Cover your eyes from delightful.
[SPEAKER_00]: It says dispel the lust in regard to delightful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Having seen a non-delightful, don't end up thinking about how non-delightful... i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: don't end up evolving... developing aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to non-delightful, mental aversion, but it doesn't say run away from the non-delightful because, you know, that is the way out.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That means you're blaming non-delightful and you're blaming delightful for your lust and for your aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing it where it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: By not seeing it where it is, you cannot possibly uproot it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having heard sounds both pleasant and noisy, do not be enthralled by pleasant sound, dispel the course of hate towards the noise, and do not soil the mind by thinking, this one is displeasing to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having smelt a fragrant, delightful scent, and having smelt a putrid stench, dispel aversion towards the stench, and do not yield to desire for the lovely.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having enjoyed a sweet, delicious taste, and having sometimes tasted what is bitter, do not greedily enjoy the sweet taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do not feel aversion towards the bitter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it can't be clearer than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, many people blame the taste.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do not greedily enjoy the sweet taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't be greed in regard to...
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean don't ever eat sweet, agreeable taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're genuinely equanimous in regard to the taste, it doesn't matter if it's agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means, if you're genuinely equanimous, you won't be running away from agreeable, because you fear that it will induce the lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Equanimity is basically absence of lust for understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, removing of greed in regard to the agreeable, in regard to delicious, having enjoyed delicious sweet taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can even enjoy it, in a way, without being greedy about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a form of enjoyment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense enjoys it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't necessarily enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's obvious that many people don't enjoy it because they fear it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's a mistake.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you let the sense enjoy it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you have to eat.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you don't do it unwarily, you don't do it carelessly, because that will then induce greed in your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you will be appropriating sense that enjoys it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't enjoy the taste even if you want to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always pertains to the
[SPEAKER_00]: Like that physical sense, presence of the matter, that is your tongue.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the fact that you think that you can enjoy it, and then you deny it, through running away, through practicing extreme asceticism, through not eating, because, you know, you fear the taste, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are fully appropriating your sense base, and then protecting it, because you can't let go of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The hunter's chasing you, kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've been chased.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're running away.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't sort of... Well, no, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, in a sense, you can't run away, because you're holding on to the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, OK. You're not eating it, because you're fearing it, but you're holding on to it, which amounts to the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're hooked by the bait, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either through eating it carelessly, or through, like, holding it tightly out of fear.
[SPEAKER_01]: We've seen it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can never see that actually you can't even enjoy the taste, even if you want to, that the sense will enjoy the taste, for as long as you deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as you deny agreeable taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you know for a fact that you're restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know for a fact that you eat once a day.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know for a fact that you're not seeking out for a pleasant taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you get... you encounter a pleasant taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: And feeling that is just basically complete lack of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Running away from it, it's even further lack of wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trying to prevent it, trying to not feel it with your tongue or whatever, is just plain ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those objects or the senses
[SPEAKER_01]: For the senses, in their domain, it's the kind of... it's their business, kind of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whatever they get...
[SPEAKER_00]: The five animals, they have feeding grounds.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's not...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, you will be affected by it when you appropriate that feeding ground, when you appropriate that animal that feeds them.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you are... when your mind is inseparable from your tongue, when your tongue is appropriated, when your eyes are appropriated, you will be... well, you will be affected by what you see, what you taste, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And running away from it is just another form of being affected by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no matter what comes into the eye, so to speak, no matter what you see...
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, in the scene, there is a scene, and then you will not be dead by which.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being dead by which, in another sutta, when Ananda says, it's the eye, eye, as the organ, makes you dead, by which you are the conceiver.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the one who sees the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you end up conceiving them as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, because you just automatically appropriated the sense bases, because they don't... they don't appear as objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're always negative in regard to it, which means they're even harder to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: They have to be seen as a negative phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, most people don't see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, because of their appropriation of their sense base, in this case, let's say, eyes, they are the seer of the eye objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they just descended down into the eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: They took that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now, what I see, means I see that.
[SPEAKER_00]: What my tongue tastes, I'm tasting that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's to mean they're being that by which.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if seen, there is just the seen, in taste, there's just the taste, they will not be that by which.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they're not that by which, when they don't appropriate the sense organs, well, they will not be in the objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they're not appropriating sense organs, nor are they found in the objects, they will neither be here, nor yonder, nor between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: No behind, in front, above, left or right.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will simply not be room for the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because sense of self cannot arise without the basis which is appropriation, regarding things as mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that's completely prevented, through understanding that it's impossible to be there in the first place, you can't own those things in the first place,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you prevent the appropriation, means there is no room for sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't even think, oh, now I have to practice the non-self.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That experience of non-appropriation is the experience of non-self.
[SPEAKER_01]: We take, like, there's some of those animals, and the senses as the animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the dog is eating its food, but if you
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never have that food that the dog is eating, because you're not... you're not the dog.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not the dog, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you thought you were holding on to the dog, you know, and thinking that you are eating this food, whatever it is, but that's... you can't get any of that stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're going to be suffering constantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, think of it like this, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way for you to eat the food is for tongue, mouth, digestive organ to engage with the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of those things, if you look at them independently, so to speak, are independent of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your mouth, your organ, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... it's not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if those things have arisen and they correspond... well, they have objects that correspond to it, they're engaged with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not recognizing the impermanence of the sense bases, for example, you appropriate it automatically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the similar... the animals...
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't quite work in this sense, because you can always... well, nothing stops you from eating dog food.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the thing is, there are five animals, but basically, you know the domains because of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't... you can't have... you cannot have a relationship with sight without the eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, basically, all you can have a relationship with is... all you can have a relationship with is eyes seeing things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't access sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: Unless I see them first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't even have the idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even mentally think about sights without implying eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you don't appropriate your eye, then your eye is going to just look at... it's going to be unrestrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what people think.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they think, oh, so I must let go of my eyes, which means...
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, you're still... you are responsible for restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you start restraining, and the precepts are quite clear, whether 5, whether 8, whether 10, no matter how many, they're quite clear, and that's what you decided beforehand, and then you start seeing the negative phenomenon of the eye, eye object, sorry, eye base, eye basis, the sense basis of the eyes, and then you recognize, okay, so it's still within that restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you were now to make the jump from non-appropriation of the eye to a non-restraint of the eye,
[SPEAKER_00]: That would have to be a conscious jump.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can't happen by accident.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because eyes stopped engaging in unwholesome, fully unwholesome things through setting up the sīla first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now you can genuinely let go of the eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they won't go into that unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they used to go into unwholesome only because you are sending them there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, really.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Buddha said you can't possibly engage in sensuality
[SPEAKER_00]: Without having fully established sensual perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for that, you're fully responsible.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that cannot be done without appropriation of the eyes.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, quite the opposite from what people believe.
[SPEAKER_00]: Genuinely letting go, genuinely not appropriating the eye base, fully prevents even a possibility of sensual engagement.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that is intentional, once the eyes have been taken as mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you relish the life, the pleasure that you fully feel you can access.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole nature of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You feel you're in touch with your disagreeable objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either through consuming them through your mouth, through your eyes, through your nose, through grasping them with your hands.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly what sensuality is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Consumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can only assume that you can consume things when you have appropriated basis that they're the only ones that can access them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even then, all you're consuming, assuming that you're consuming, are the sense bases that then, on their own external kind of level, correspond to these sense objects and interact with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can never actually access the sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you can have is... all you can see, so to speak, is I seeing things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Already doing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you can have is your sense base being affected by these things, but you can't access those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't actually taste the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can taste your tongue tasting the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't touch things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can experience your body being touched by things or your body touching things.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it's always indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can never bypass the body as a sense of touch or bypass the tongue and go straight to the sense objects, which means the sense objects
[SPEAKER_00]: Our color is always determined by your sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if your eyes are not seeing certain colors, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even conceive those colors.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even conceive... Only like in some... like maybe external communication might get the idea that you're seeing things differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for you, that is what you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the real thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can only access senses that are being affected by external objects, by external matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that recognition already uproots any desire you can have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they're inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how hard you press, how hard you squeeze, how hard you taste, how hard you look, you know, you're fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't doubt it anymore that all you're seeing is your eyes seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you're tasting is your tongue tasting.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you're touching is your body touching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's always an indirect.
[SPEAKER_00]: An indirect manner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't turn away, turn back and look at the things.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way you can see them is by having a mirror in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's your way of looking back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this simile, looking back is basically the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are out there in the world, inaccessible.
[SPEAKER_00]: The only way to access them is when they are reflected upon the sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: When they engage, there's a corresponding engagement with the sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: How it corresponded to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it still doesn't mean you're actually accessing the matter of the sense objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will require you to come out of all of your sense bases and then go straight to the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even that thought is based on a complete experience of sense bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even imaginary bases.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even in your imagination.
[SPEAKER_01]: In a
[SPEAKER_01]: Six... something with the six animals.
[SPEAKER_01]: Five.
[SPEAKER_01]: Six... five.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't remember what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: Crocodile, human.
[SPEAKER_00]: Crocodile, monkey.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I forgot.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they... Is it six?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's five animals and then the mind, where they meet in the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the five senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think it's six because it's the monkey.
[SPEAKER_01]: He says the monkey is the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, maybe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: They they pull to their own feeding grounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the thing is, he's got a... there's a rope tied.
[SPEAKER_01]: He ties the rope in the middle, and then they just pull.
[SPEAKER_01]: And whoever's ever the strongest, that's where everyone else will go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everyone else goes, yeah, because they're tied to the same, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So everyone goes where the crocodile falls, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, he doesn't just tie it in the middle, he ties it to a post.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's discernment, that's mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, they get tired.
[SPEAKER_01]: They stop pulling it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they can't actually go there, because they're tired.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, that's similar to the fact that, like, you don't... you don't tie it in the middle together, because then the strongest will pull.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's basically when people use a certain sense to overcome other senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, unpleasant sights, sounds are bothering you, but then your mind just goes... starts thinking about pleasant taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you're both... you're bothered by unpleasant touch, unpleasant taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then you light a beautiful incense, and then you're enjoying a pleasant smell, and your mind calms down because of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or sometimes admiring the beautiful view as a form of meditation, which is as mistaken as it can be, because it's exactly, ah, this sense seems calmer than the others, so you use that sense to overcome the others, but then that sense, when that sense changes, you will be pulled, and all the other senses will go for it, because this is the strongest among them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I don't really mean going that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you must not use any sense as a basis for meditation, because that's not meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha did say that, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a jackal waiting for a mouse, or an owl waiting for a prey, preying upon a fish, like waiting, hunting, hunting, waiting, grabbing the moment, waiting, waiting, waiting.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the misguided person over-meditates, under-meditates, mis-meditates, pre-meditates, but he does meditate.
[SPEAKER_00]: And basically, when they miss the point of meditation, they end up meditating with their mind revolving around sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And revolving around sensuality means revolving around dependence on a sense, for pleasure and for pain, peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, there is nothing pleasing in a sight, nothing pleasing in a smell, no pleasing, no taste, no...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a pleasing sight, but there is no greed for the pleasure of that sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just a pleasing sight.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if there's no pleasing... but there's... the only way you can get pleasure is through, eh... is how you embody.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then you will go...
[SPEAKER_01]: In comfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will go to the... Yeah, physical comfort, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If there's no physical contact, you go and fantasize about other sides, or even just go into your imagination.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of a reproduction of the other senses in their peaceful state, in the state of not being yanked by their hunger or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's again, it revolves around them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everyone's got a... well, I suppose everyone's more inclined to certain...
[SPEAKER_01]: Senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people are prone to be shy, or some people have issues with, like, food restraint, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Music, yeah, to listen to ear, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, that's, that's another thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, people listen to music as a form of meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what I was describing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, it's, it's after, like, after the, after the misdrive.
[SPEAKER_01]: When touched by a pleasant contact, do not be enthralled.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do not tremble when touched by pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look evenly on both the pleasant and the painful, not drawn or repelled by anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: To me, that touch is quite a... it's very insight, you know, insight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's so close.
[SPEAKER_01]: Personal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it's quite a...
[SPEAKER_01]: To be able to look evenly on both pleasant and painful touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not have your mind swayed by it, by the prospect of comfort, by the possibility of discomfort, if any physical kind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being swayed means not, not, not, not, not craving it and not running away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it wasn't here to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you running away from it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why are you trying to avoid it?
[SPEAKER_00]: You trying to avoid it means, basically, you're still regarding it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: The sense bases, so you're trying to avoid things that correspond to your sense base.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're trying to to avoid comfort or discomfort, depending on your view.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you will only be committed to avoiding it, because you're fully appropriating this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of letting go of the body, relinquishing any notion of appropriation, then sometimes comfort, sometimes discomfort.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind doesn't get swayed, doesn't get affected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can feel that your whole body, well, you know, your whole body's touched.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's not appropriate, you know, you disapproach... See, that's the thing, you can't run away from that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why mindfulness of the body plays such a fundamental... because of that, and because all the other senses are basically bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all rooted, contained in this very body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you stop appropriating the body as a sense base, in this entirety, as a sixth sense base, then you won't be appropriating sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, or thoughts and images.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't be appropriating anything, physically or mentally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you don't appropriate it, you don't need to run away from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because disagreeable... agreeable was not yours to begin with.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if there is any response to agreeable, it's a bodily response.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a response of the sense base that you don't appropriate, which means it's only a limited response.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can never be a response with lust, a response with aversion, a response with delusion, because they're all intentional responses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Responses for which you and your misappropriation of things was responsible for.
[SPEAKER_01]: He continues further the same sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: When common people of proliferated perception deceive and proliferate, they become engaged.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having dispelled every mind-state bound to the home life, one travels on the road of renunciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is thus well developed in six, these six phases,
[SPEAKER_01]: If touched, one's mind never flutters anywhere, having vanquished both lust and hate.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bhikkhus go to the far shore beyond birth and death.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is another sutta, the one after.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's 95, Mulunkirt.
[SPEAKER_01]: A great monk with a great name.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, eh, he goes to the... he's quite old, apparently, at this stage, and he...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think I remember him from Manjulika.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: A layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was asking him, you know, how come sotāpanna's mind can sometimes also be affected by... by all sorts of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: He forgets about dhamma, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Also.
[SPEAKER_00]: But maybe it was a different one.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know if it was a different... yeah, but the same name.
[SPEAKER_00]: The same name, yeah
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he asked the Buddha for a short... might... so, he might... a short discourse or short message.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he might dwell alone, withdrawn, diligent, ardent, resolute.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the Buddha goes on to say, questions him.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think, Malankeya Buddha?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have any desire, lust or affection for those forms cognizable by the eye that you have not seen or never saw before?
[SPEAKER_01]: That you do not see and would not think might be seen?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you have any desire, lust or affection for those touches, cognizable by the body, that you haven't... have not touched you and never been touched by before, that you do... do not touch now and would not touch in the future?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible to have lust for things that have never
[SPEAKER_00]: For sights, they have never been seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: They will never be seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly imagine them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they've never been seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't have lust for that which hasn't arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have lust for that which
[SPEAKER_00]: has not left an imprint on a sense base, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Figuratively speaking, it isn't actually an imprint, but you can't have lust for that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's similar to what I was saying before.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, if you see that, basically, it's impossible to lust or have aversion towards sight that has never been seen, never will be seen, you can't even imagine seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you recognize that the sights that you did see, that you will see, are completely circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're far more inferior to all of the things that you haven't seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they were seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always like things that are seen always arise on a basis of greater things that haven't been seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, you realize that even your lust is completely perturbed and unnecessary and pathetic, because you're lusting this sight that was completely random and circumstantial and easily could have not been.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a big change.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you recognize that, in whatever you're experiencing, that this could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is, but could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that it could have not been precedes the fact that it is, means, oh, it's completely circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it was never for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It could have never been for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it certainly will never be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that being for me, being mine, it's already, like, makes it special, makes it, gives it priority.
[SPEAKER_00]: Makes it more important.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if something is circumstantial, ah, it could have not been, which means it won't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Something else becomes its place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when that does, that could have also not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't have lust for things that have never been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, when you do have lust for things that are, that's just on top of... that's completely gratuitous on top of that circumstantial arising.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just through recognizing that you can't have lust for things that are never... have never arisen, you can actually abandon lust for things that have, by seeing their circumstantial nature, which is nothing other than saying by seeing arisen things as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And impermanent means impossible to own, means
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, subject to cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subject to cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doesn't mean you're actually witnessing their cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just recognize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is circumstantial, which means you have no idea where it came from, and because of that, it will cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you keep witnessing it for the rest of your life, it still remains impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: That covers everything that might be seen.
[SPEAKER_00]: It covers all the possibilities as well, because whatever might be seen, it's going to be seen like this, on a circumstantial basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... that's the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you... if you don't cover it, if you don't know that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: The danger is... You left things unincluded, basically, in this reflection, yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a... a couple, let's say, a man and a woman get together.
[SPEAKER_01]: They love each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: Infatuated with each other.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh, he's, you know, he's seen her, but he he might see someone else tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: There might be even more desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he can't stop that from happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can shut off his eyes, but then... Yeah, because you never practice restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: You go after things he sees, things he touches, things he pins his eyes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he loses interest in his wife.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: He just moves on to another.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he were to see that even the first one was completely circumstantial,
[SPEAKER_00]: He would have... well, he would have been able to control his desire, if not completely abandon it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a reason for abandoning.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what I'm saying is that even a layperson, not necessarily a monk who is practicing for arahantship, even a layperson, who is in the union with the opposite sex, can use this reflection to remain faithful, to remain restrained, to remain... to develop wisdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's that sutta where the couple, the man and woman, came to the Buddha, and
[SPEAKER_00]: And they asked him how to... and I think they were... they might both have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha... About how to be reborn together?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, I'm not sure if it was answered how to be reborn together, but it was basically sort of... he says, oh, yeah, they practice, like, perfect... they're perfectly faithful to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, not just... they've never...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, husband says, not just that he never cheated on the wife, but he also never, never, never, like, verbally was unfaithful to her, and he was never even unfaithful to her, even in his mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: And she says the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't mean that he never saw a prettier woman.
[SPEAKER_00]: It simply means that they recognized, like, the intentional aspect of their desire, of their choice, and they clearly respected each other, and they just, okay, there was a more pleasing sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But more pleasing sight does not mean lust is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust is there when you're careless in regard to the more pleasing sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they were never careless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, they were never unfaithful to each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha praised it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's exactly how somebody who wants to be in union should live.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can see that's already quite a... quite a good degree of wisdom that most people today, an average person, just... it's inconceivable for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because what you see, you just go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then even though love, union, marriage, just remains utterly random and circumstantial based on just things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, people divorce.
[SPEAKER_00]: People end up hating each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they just follow the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: They are now either aging, or got bored with it, or found something better.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, the whole kind of notion of marriage and commitment is sort of now basically hindering it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they feel enslaved by their own choices, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they only have themselves to blame.
[SPEAKER_01]: Fantastic.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in this sutta, again, he goes into the... in the scene there, Shogun, just the scene.
[SPEAKER_01]: He gives you that short teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, Malankeya Putta, he says, I understand in detail, Venerable Sir, the meaning of what was stated by the Blessed One.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he gives, he says this verse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the Buddha agrees with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: Good, good, Malankeya Putta, it is good that you understand in detail the meaning of what was stated by me in brief.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just read down.
[SPEAKER_01]: When seeing a sight, mindfulness becomes confused, if attention is focused on the pleasant aspect.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing it with a mind full of desire, one remains assuming to it, clinging to it, assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many feelings grow, arising from sights.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, back to the beginning of the verse, so it says, quite clearly, that wrongly attending to the pleasant sight,
[SPEAKER_00]: Desire and lust and assumption grows in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not just by merely having a pleasant sight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means pleasant sight or unpleasant sight was never the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's you don't know
[SPEAKER_00]: Not knowing how to attend to it, you end up being confused.
[SPEAKER_00]: Being confused, you end up assuming.
[SPEAKER_00]: Assuming the whole desire, the whole... the whole, basically, thing ends up proliferating and growing more and more.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, yeah, just...
[SPEAKER_01]: Many feelings grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Many...
[SPEAKER_00]: Upon giving in to pleasure, you might sometimes experience more pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, by trying to run away from that pain, you discover some new pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that was all based on the initial confusion in regard to pleasant side, which you, like, ignorantly craved for and went for, desired for, delighted in, lusted after.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, you just created basis for now all sorts of pleasant, unpleasant, neutral.
[SPEAKER_00]: And giving into that, you create more basis for pleasant pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, feelings grow.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just...
[SPEAKER_01]: By cutting it off right there in that pleasant experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can take anything, no matter how proliferated it is, you can actually uproot it in its entirety, if you see the nature of craving towards pleasure, of nature, nature of avoiding, having aversion towards displeasure, the nature of indolence towards neither pleasure nor displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding the nature of it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, that just pertains, permeates the whole, no matter how proliferated the picture is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, basically, you kill the roots, you kill the proliferating life that was being fed by ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You dry it up, and then it's like a palm stump.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the proliferated tree branches remain petrified.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't spread anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ignorance doesn't fuel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, now it's just dried up habits of certain kind, the ones that were completely dependent upon sensuality, fall off.
[SPEAKER_00]: But some of it remains, until the aggregates break apart completely, for another end.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want someone's pure... obviously, you want feelings to grow, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like in the... the pleasure, do you want it to get more, more?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's why... that's why, see, that's why sometimes people like to kind of expose themselves to the risk of this pleasure, because it makes that pleasure even greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, within a pleasant, non-threatening situation, you kind of want to spice it up, so to speak, and then you make yourself kind of liable to some pain as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's all within the pleasurable image that you're already fully engaged with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you know, overcoming challenges and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only engage that on the basis of pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: If the whole thing suddenly turns, and then the whole thing becomes life-threatening,
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now it's serious.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you stop engaging in the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, that's why people, you know, go after freedom, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even go after risk that, you know, makes them experience displeasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's all within the image of pleasure that they've initially given into and then proliferated.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Initially, given into aversion in regard to this pleasure, even if you start experiencing pleasure on top of it, you won't be appreciating it, because, you know, the mind is upset, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, feelings grow on top of each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if you stop, establish mindfulness, all you can say is that a feeling is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if it's the top of the proliferated tree or the bottom.
[SPEAKER_00]: A feeling has arisen, which means every feeling
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how many of them have grown, how many of them have spread, proliferated, got established, every feeling carries the nature of feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, in regard to every feeling, you can practice abandoning of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: They all carry the principle, the nature, the universal principle, which this principle feeds on further.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to chase all these proliferating feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they're trying to trim all these branches that are constantly growing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly keep up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead, just kill the roots.
[SPEAKER_00]: Uproot it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Remove the food from the ground that the roots are sucking onto.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: They die.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to worry about the branches spreading anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know for sure they won't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you don't know where exactly their proliferating got so big.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you know that you've killed the roots, one way or the other, and the tree's not being fed proliferation stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, one task, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: As opposed to trying to manage, contain, direct, fashion, the branches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, manage.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's form of management.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is that many feelings grow, arising from sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is damaged by covetousness and cruelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Heaping up suffering like this is said to be far from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: When hearing a sound, mindfulness becomes confused.
[SPEAKER_01]: If attention is focused on the pleasant aspect, experiencing with a mind full of desire, one remains assuming to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Many feelings grow, arising from sounds.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is damaged by covetousness and cruelty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping up suffering like this is said to be far from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: When smelling a smell, when savoring a taste, when touching a touch,
[SPEAKER_01]: When knowing a mental phenomenon, it continues, you know, that mind is damaged and is far from nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then he goes on to say, seeing a sight with mindfulness, there is no desire for sights.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing it with the mind free of desire, one doesn't remain assuming to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it is for someone who lives mindfully, when repeatedly seeing a sight, feeling is ended, not added to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reducing suffering like this is said to be in the presence of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they see then, by seeing, by being mindful in regard to pleasant sight, mindful in regard to unpleasant sight, so he neither develops lust nor aversion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindful in regard to neutral, neither agreeable nor disagreeable sight,
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't develop indolence, he doesn't develop ignorance, he doesn't develop delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means all those feelings that arise simultaneously with that, he understands as they arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he doesn't add to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: He... and basically adding to them means he doesn't induce craving in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what means ending of the feeling as it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because when you create a feeling, obviously, you go further, and then you experience another feeling on account of that, and then another feeling on account of that, and it's just all piling up, so to speak, further, increasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're mindful in regard to sights, the feeling that has arisen, that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see it as impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: By seeing it as impermanent, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're mindful in regard to sights,
[SPEAKER_00]: There won't be any craving in regard to that feeling, because craving requires notion of permanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Be it craving for pleasure or craving for avoiding of pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by removing the craving, you stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop assuming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Touching a touch with mindfulness, there's no desire for touches.
[SPEAKER_01]: Experiencing with the mind fear of desire, one doesn't remain assuming to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: As it is for someone who lives mindfully, when repeatedly touching a touch, feeling is ended, not added to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reducing suffering like this is said to be in the presence of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just want to read that one out, because there's a difference between touch and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, I feel something in my back.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, you're touching something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or a sensation in my knees.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that sensation is perception of the touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not a feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: People think sensations are feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensations are perceptions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like I said, repeatedly practicing mindfulness in regard to it, it uplifts it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reducing suffering like this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Reducing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because suffering can arise only on the basis of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: And craving can arise only on the basis of ignorance in regard to feelings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And ignorance in regard to feelings can arise only on the basis of non-mindfully attending to pleasure, non-mindfully attending to pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you're touched by the feeling.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're touched by the feeling, you crave in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by mindfully attending to what's seen, what's heard, what's tasted, what's touched, what's thought, by mindfully attending to it repetitively, the desire and lust in regard to it diminishes, aversion diminishes, which means that feelings are not entertained, not engaged, not craved for.
[SPEAKER_01]: But each sight and so on is either agreeable or disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, neither agreeable nor disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's always felt.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Perception and feeling are conjoined.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just have perception and feeling coming later.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the mind is determined by perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: So experiencing an agreeable
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you can say there is an agreeable feeling corresponding to it, but that still doesn't mean that you're touched by pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you're ignorant in regard to agreeable feeling, you basically... you're touched by pleasure, which means you crave for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the craving is the inclination or the push towards... inclination towards... Yeah, I mean, it's subtler, like just leaning of the mind towards, leaning away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kravan for, Kravan against.